<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writer &amp;amp; Geek Show</title>
    <description>We are Writer &amp; Geek, we make our listeners get excited about boring stuff one episode at a time. Writer and Geek Show is a science and tech podcast and we love geeking about tech, history, science, music and any other topic they can think of. In this show, we discuss a variety of topics and ramble on and on about them.
</description>
    <link>https://writerandgeek.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://writerandgeek.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 23:24:32 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 23:24:32 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The History of Vaccum Cleaner</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;vacuum-cleaner&quot;&gt;Vacuum Cleaner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vacuum cleaner, also known as a sweeper or hoover, is a device that uses an air pump to create a partial vacuum to suck up dust and dirt, usually from floors, and from other surfaces.
Basically, it is a device which sucks your home tidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2300 B.C. - First rudimentary forms of broom and cleaning tools came into existence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1797 - Levi Dickenson devised a broom with the use of sorghum bristles. The sorghum broom business exploded and by 1860 sorghum got the name broomcorn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1858 - Hiram Herrick patented a carpet sweeper which was the first American patent for a carpet sweeper. The device consisted of a rolling broom and dustpan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1860 - Daniel Hess produced a carpet sweeper which used suction through a rotating brush and bellows. It was completely manual and that is probably the reason why it was not successful. It was the first rudimentary design of a vacuum cleaner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1869 - Ives W. McCaffe came up with ‘Whirlwind’, the first manual vacuum cleaner which was upright. The belt driven, hand-powered device was sold for a retail price of $25 which would be around a whopping $450 in the present. This proved to be the reason for the unsuccessful run of the device.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1898 - A gasoline powered blower was developed by John S. Thurman, which had to be horse-drawn to locations due to its bulky nature. It was a moderately successful device which relied on blowing the dust into a receptacle instead of suction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1901 - Hubert Cecil Booth from England manufactured the ‘Puffing Billy’ which was also a bulky device but relied on suction. The gasoline-powered machine was later upgraded to electric power. It used a cloth filter to collect the dust. Puffing Billy was extremely successful and hotels started installing it in their compound. It was once also used to clean West Minister Abbey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During the same time, David T. Kenney came up with a vacuum cleaner which was powered by steam engine. But it did not succeed in getting much business due to its weight of 4000 pounds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1906 - Walter Griffiths came up with the first portable vacuum cleaner which used bellows and flexible pipe for suction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1906 -  Jame B. Kirby developed a vacuum cleaner that used water for dirt separation instead of a filter. It was called ‘Domestic Cyclone’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1907 - James Murray Spangler, a janitor from Ohio devised a vacuum cleaner with the use of a broom, electric rotating motor, and a pillowcase for dust collection. Because he did not get the funding, he sold the patent to William Henry Hoover in 1908.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1926 - Hoover redesigned the vacuum cleaner by adding a steel box for sturdiness and disposal filter bags to collect dust. It became a mainstay in the market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1997 - A Swedish company came up with ‘Electrolux Trilobite’, the first autonomous cordless robotic vacuum cleaner. This was made available to the consumers in 2001.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2004 - A British company came up with ‘Airider’, a vacuum cleaner which uses the technology of hovercrafts to float above the floor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@creativeexchange?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from The Creative Exchange&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;The Creative Exchange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 11:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/052-vaccum-cleaner/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/052-vaccum-cleaner/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ice-cream</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;ice-and-cream&quot;&gt;Ice and cream&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No introduction required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a colloidal emulsion which is made into a foam by incorporating air and then frozen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice cream is a mixture of water, ice, milk fat, milk protein, sugar and air.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The mixture is stirred well to incorporate air and is cooled below the freezing point and stored as semi-solid foam stored at low temperatures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accepted composition of ice-cream in the US according to Wikipedia (all percentages by weight):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater than 10% milkfat and usually between 10% and as high as 16% fat in some premium ice creams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9 to 12% milk solids-not-fat: this component, also known as the serum solids, contains the proteins (caseins and whey proteins) and carbohydrates (lactose) found in milk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 to 16% sweeteners: usually a combination of sucrose and glucose-based corn syrup sweeteners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2 to 0.5% stabilisers and emulsifiers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;55% to 64% water, which comes from the milk or other ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ice cream was consumed during the Achaemenid Empire in 500 BC. Ice was mixed with flavours and consumed during the summertime.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Persians also invented a dish with ice, rose water and vermicelli which was a primitive version of &lt;strong&gt;Falooda&lt;/strong&gt;. This was mostly reserved for the Royals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greeks weren’t behind, they also invented snow mixed with honey and fruits which was also sold in the markets of Athens.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hippocrates advocated eating ice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;China invented the real primitive form of ice-cream using milk and rice around 200 B.C. Snow and saltpetre was poured outside of containers filled with syrups to reduce the melting point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A few centuries later, during the time of Nero, ice was bought from the mountains to Rome and combines with fruits and served as delicacies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marco Polo bought the recipe back to Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In India, ice was shipped in from Hindukush mountains and used in sorbets and in making &lt;em&gt;Kulfi&lt;/em&gt; which came into existence around 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italian Dutchess Catherine de Medici married Henry II of France in 1533 and bought some Italian chef’s along with her who made flavoured ice. Flavoured ice became popular in France.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italian Francesco dei Coltelli opened an ice cream café in 1651 in Paris which became popular. During the next 50 years around 250 cafés opened in Paris.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charles I of England was fond of ice-cream and paid his chef to not to give away the recipe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the mid-eighteenth century, ice-cream became popular in the United States as well. George Washington was a big fan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the mid-nineteenth century, ice-cream became inexpensive and available to common people. This was mainly due to Carlo Gatti setting up a stand outside of Strand in 1851. He sold a scoop for one penny. He imported ice from Norway.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agnes Marshall popularised many ice-cream recipes in England.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice-cream appeared in Greece in 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;production&quot;&gt;Production&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Before refrigerators, ice-cream was meant only for the rich upper class. Ice was hard to come by.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice-cream was made in using the &lt;em&gt;pot freeze&lt;/em&gt; method where a large bowl was kept in a tub of ice and salt.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The mixture of salt and ice cooled the temperature of the ingredients within the bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salt partially melts the ice allowing it to absorb the latent heat and thus brings the temperature of the ingredients below the freezing point of water. This helps in freezing milk which has a lower freezing point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First, large-scale production in the US was by Jacob Fussell of Baltimore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;types&quot;&gt;Types&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sundae&lt;/strong&gt;: A type of ice-cream with one or more scoop of cream and syrup. It was a variation of ice-cream soda and due to restrictions on consuming soda on Sundays, soda was replaced with syrup. To avoid religious conflict changed the spelling to “ice-cream sundae”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice-cream cone&lt;/strong&gt;: Agnes Marshall’s cookery book had a recipe for serving ice cream in cones, but the practice is believed to be existing before that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Faludah or Faloodeh&lt;/strong&gt;: Popular Iranian ice-cream with vermicelli, rose water and sugar syrup.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gelato&lt;/strong&gt;: Italian frozen dessert with a lower milk fat content than ice cream.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice-cream sandwich&lt;/strong&gt;: A bar of ice-cream sandwiched between two cookies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frozen yoghurt&lt;/strong&gt;: Made with yoghurt instead of milk or cream.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;present-day&quot;&gt;Present day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US is the major consumer of ice-cream with about 23 litres per capita followed by Australia and New Zealand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;India is one of the largest producers of ice-cream and most of the production is consumed domestically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@harniche?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Harnish Ganatra&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Harnish Ganatra&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 11:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/051-ice-cream/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/051-ice-cream/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cryptography ft. Rupen Paul</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;thats-50&quot;&gt;That’s 50!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 50&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; episode, we sit down and talk with Rupen Paul, the star stand up comedian and upcoming podcaster about cryptography. This was a pleasant evening with rain, coffee and snacks. Occassional chewing noises are to be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sit back and enjoy our version of cryptography!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rupens-right-room&quot;&gt;Rupen’s Right Room&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rupen is also the host of an amazing podcast and we think that you should definitely check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/channel/the-right-room&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Right Room Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;books-mentioned&quot;&gt;Books mentioned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that these are affiliate links where we get paid a percentage for each purchase and this helps us in the production of the show. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2BQH6b4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Enigma: The Battle For The Code (Hugh Sebag-Montefiore)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Lxg7RC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Digital Fortress by Dan Brown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2PF4z1G&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sherlock Holmes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@mr_williams_photography?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Micah Williams&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Micah Williams&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/050-cryptography/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/050-cryptography/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An update on the flood situation</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;update&quot;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a quick update on the flood situation in Kerala and Karnataka:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Lrh4HlpQrI8?rel=0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the overwhelming support. Kerala and Karnataka need our support to get through the tough times due to heavy rains and floods. Let us continue our solidarity irrespective of religion, region, caste, language and other diversity. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@laicho?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Cherry Laithang&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Cherry Laithang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/flood-update/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/flood-update/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Serial Killer Files Part 5: Cyanide Mohan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mohan Kumar, infamously known as Cyanide Mohan is a serial killer who targeted women by offering them marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;details&quot;&gt;Details:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DOB: 1963&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place: Mangalore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marital status: Married thrice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Span of crime: 2005-2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of victims: 20&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Date of apprehension: October 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crime-history&quot;&gt;Crime history&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cyanide Mohan worked as a primary school teacher from 1980 to 2003.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He was fired from his job for allegedly pushing a woman off the Nethravathi when she refused his marriage proposal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The motive of the murders were to satisfy his sexual needs and to extort the valuables from his victims.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He used cyanide laced pills to kill his victims.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convicted for 5 murders of the 20 murders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He is his own attorney and successful appealed to convert one death penalty into a life sentence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He is also found to have committed bank frauds and forgeries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently serving two death penalties and two life sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@rawpixel?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from rawpixel&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;rawpixel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/049-serial-killer-cynide-mohan/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/049-serial-killer-cynide-mohan/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A request</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;kerala-needs-our-help&quot;&gt;Kerala needs our help&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kerala has been hit with torrential rains over past few weeks and things are getting really difficult down there. In this short conversation, we request you to be a part in helping to rebuild the God’s own country. Honourable Chief Minister of Kerala tweeted the details on how you can contribute to this cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://donation.cmdrf.kerala.gov.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chief Minister’s Distress Relief Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Here&amp;#39;s how you can help those affected by the unprecedented floods in Kerala. Now you can make donations online to Chief Minister&amp;#39;s Distress Relief Fund through the site,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/OFHTHlZ9by&quot;&gt;https://t.co/OFHTHlZ9by&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/KeralaFloods?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#KeralaFloods&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/StandWithKerala?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#StandWithKerala&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/XNlBKqdCUT&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/XNlBKqdCUT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; CMO Kerala (@CMOKerala) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CMOKerala/status/1029363568725110784?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 14, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@laicho?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Cherry Laithang&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Cherry Laithang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/a-request/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/a-request/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jet Engines</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;love-em-planes-️&quot;&gt;Love ‘em planes ✈️&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jet engine is a type of internal combustion engine that produces thrust based on a fast moving discharge of hot gases, widely used on airplanes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hero of Alexandria built Aeopile which was the earliest for of jet engine dating back to 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century A.D.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was a steam turbine which rotated when a central water container is heated. Much like a lawn sprinkler.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was more of a curiousity thing and did not have practical application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chinese invented rocket fireworks in the 13&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, but since these were inefficient, did not develop for few more centuries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-need&quot;&gt;The need&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The propeller driven airplanes had their limitations in terms of max speed that could be achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pressure build up while approaching sound barrier caused many of these planes to crash.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-components&quot;&gt;Key components&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Air intake&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compressor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gas turbine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combustion chamber&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exhaust nozzle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;types-of-jet-engines&quot;&gt;Types of Jet Engines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turbojet&lt;/strong&gt;: Basically a gas turbine that compresser air through an inlet and compressor. Fuel is mixed with th compressed air in the combustion chamber and the exhaust gases propel the engine forward and also run the compressor. All the ir passes through the inlet into the compressor, the combustion chamber and then through the turbines before escaping out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turboprop&lt;/strong&gt;: Turboprop uses the exhaust to mainly drive a propeller that provides the thrust to move the engine forward. In this type of engine, the jet thrust is augmented by the propeller. They perform extremely well at low speeds. Another type of turboprop called turboshaft utilises all the power to run the propeller and produces almost no jet exhaust. This mainly used to power helicopters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turbofan&lt;/strong&gt;: Turbofan is essentially a turbojet with a giant fan in the front of the compressor. The fan draws more ait and while a part of it enters the inlet, the rest of it goes around the engine providing additional thrust in a way similar to a turboprop. This is the way more efficient than a turbojet. The fan allows greater thrust at low speeds. In passenger jets, the engines have a biger fan and helps in reduced noise and increased efficiency whereas in military aircraft where flight is usually supersonic and noise isn’t a factor, turbofans with smaller fans are used to reduce drag and increase the menouverability of the craft.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ramjet&lt;/strong&gt;: Ramjet does not use a compressor instead depends on the air pressure to build up at the inlet duct. As a result, a ramject cannot work in subsonic speeds and requires it to be accelerated to supersonic speeds by a turbojet or a rocket engine. Practical applications are in missiles and unmanned vehicles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shoutout&quot;&gt;Shoutout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.storiyoh.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Storiyoh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://podhead.co/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Podhead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/posts/6962992-tms-030-explore-kochi-with-johann-kuruvilla&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Musafir Stories - Kochi episode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@owencavlys?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Owen CL&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Owen CL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/048-jet-engines/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/048-jet-engines/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pizza</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-mighty&quot;&gt;It’s mighty!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pizza is undoubtedly one of the most loved food in the world. About 7 billion pizzas are consumed across the world every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Its history can be traced back to the streets of Naples, Italy in the Dark Ages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The introduction of tomato and mozzarella cheese revolutionised the art of pizza making.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first pizzeria was set up in 1830 and is called Antica Pizzeria Port’Alba. Yes, it still exists.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As per legend, Margherita Pizza was invented by Raffaele Esposito in 1889 for Queen Margherita. It was made using tomatoes, mozzarella cheese, and basil leaves which represents the colours of the Italian flag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pizza-and-usa&quot;&gt;Pizza and USA:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G. Lombardi, the first pizzeria in the US was set up in 1905&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;World War II popularised pizza in the country.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 billion pizzas consumed by Americans every year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;251,770,000 pounds of pepperoni consumed by Americans every year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a $32 billion business in the country every year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pizza results in 41% increase in cheese consumption since 1995 in US.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NASA 3D printed a pizza in 2013 (What? Really?!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;health-benefits&quot;&gt;Health Benefits:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unlike popular belief, pizza is not always unhealthy. If it is made with the right ingredients it can have many health benefits. It reduces the risk of oesophagal, colon, oral cavity, and pharyngeal cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;random-facts&quot;&gt;Random facts:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First pineapple pizza (Hawaiian pizza) and the frozen pizza was made in 1962.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Largest pizza was made in 2012 in Rome and it measured 1261 square metres.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dog Pizza, also known as Heaven Scent Pizza, is made using flour, carrots, celery, and parmesan cheese.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cambodian Happy Pizza is made using marijuana&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some of the strange pizza flavours include potato chips, ice cream, beer, e-cigarette, and condoms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are you waiting for? Go eat some pizza!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@iavnt?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from ivan Torres&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;ivan Torres&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 23:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/047-pizza/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/047-pizza/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An update</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-update&quot;&gt;An update&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief update on the Writer &amp;amp; Geek Show. We have been on a sabbatical since we completed a year of podcasting. But we are using this time to improve our show and our website. We plan to come back with more episodes starting August. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Shankar and Vishnu&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/an-update/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/an-update/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deconstructing Formula One</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-top-notch&quot;&gt;The top notch&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Formula one is the highest class of racing sanctioned by FIA.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The inaugural season was in 1950.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A season consists of races called Grand Prix (Grand Prize in French).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Formula” is set of rules to be followed by the manufacturers and the drivers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One of the fastest type of races owing to the aerodynamic design of cars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grand Prix Motor Racing&lt;/strong&gt;: A precursor to the modern day Formula One racing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started in France in 1894. Involved racing from one town to the next.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evolved into endurance races.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High rate of fatality owing to poor safety standards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post World War II, evolved into Formula One.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was a medium for car manufacturers to promote their cars. French has special interest in motor cars.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First racing took place on &lt;strong&gt;July 22, 1894&lt;/strong&gt; organised by &lt;strong&gt;Le Petit Journal&lt;/strong&gt; between Paris and Rouen distance of 126 km.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count Jules-Albert de Dion&lt;/strong&gt; won the race in 6 hours 48 minutes at an average speed of 19 km/h (12 mph) and 3 mins the 30s ahead of the runner-up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;James Gordon Bennett Jr.&lt;/strong&gt;, who was the owner of New York Herald, started the Gordon Bennett cup which was an international event with countries participating against each other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each country entered up to three cars in the even and the cars were fully manufactured in those particular countries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each country had their racing colours (Green for UK, Red for Italy etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After fatalities in the Paris-Madrid race, a closed circuit was used in Ireland at Athy in 1903 and was the first closed circuit race.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grand-prix&quot;&gt;Grand Prix&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automobile Club de France&lt;/strong&gt; organised regular races that were called Grad Prix races starting 1906.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A circuit which was roughly triangular in shape situated in Le Mans was used with a lap distance of 105 km.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A total of six laps were required to be covered per day with a lap taking around an hour of each car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use of the circuit was a direct result of the 1903 Paris-Madrid race which resulted in the death of drivers and pedestrians were killed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Races were mostly nationalistic and had cars with 50hp, 10-15L engines. Each car carried a mechanic along with a driver and they were the only ones allowed to work on the car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renault won the Grand Prix by using detachable wheel rims developed by Michelin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pre-world-war-ii-days&quot;&gt;Pre World War II days&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monaco Grand Prix was the first time race grid was determined by using qualifying time rather than using a lucky draw.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the late 1930s, mechanics had long gone and cars were single seaters. Also, they were 600hp 8 or 16 cylindered monsters by this time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mercedes and Auto Union dominated due to support from Nazis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-war&quot;&gt;Post war&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post war, Formula One took shape in 1950.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Due to economic difficulties, 1952 and 53 races were held using Formula 2 cars.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Word Championship race was held on May 13 in Silverstone, UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first championship was won by Italian Giuseppe (Nino) Farina driving an Alfa Romeo in 1950 defeating Juan Manuel Fangio.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fangio later went on to win five world championships which were a record for 45 years until Schumacher broke the record in 2003.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-routine&quot;&gt;The routine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usually 12 teams compete with two drivers each.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Race weekend consists of &lt;em&gt;free practice&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;qualifying session&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To participate in a race, a driver should complete at least one lap in the free practice session.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free practice usually happens on Fridays except for Monaco Grand Prix, where the practice happens on Thursday and Fridays are reserved for other activities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Qualifying consists of three sessions namely &lt;em&gt;Q1, Q2 and Q3&lt;/em&gt;. Cars are ranked according to their lap time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During Q1 and Q2, 7 drivers are eliminated respectively leaving 10 drivers in Q3.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The driver with the fastest time gets the &lt;em&gt;pole&lt;/em&gt; position - the first on the grid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After qualification, cars are inclosed park, meaning that no significant changes can be done to the settings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Top ten cars have to start using the same tires that they set the lap times on. In few cases they can be replaced by a set of similar tyres subject to approvals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the race day, the cars are aligned on the grid according to the grid locations decided as per qualifying on the previous day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Race is usually held around 2 pm on the Sunday for most of the European races. Some races like Singapore and Abu Dhabi happen during the evenings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of laps is selected so that the total distance is more than 305 km except for Monaco where the minimum race distance is set at 260km. Also the race time cannot exceed 2 hours and in case that happens the race positions at the 2 hour mark would be considered to be the final grid positions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-car&quot;&gt;The car&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;engine&quot;&gt;Engine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The chassis is made using carbon fibre and other ultralight materials to save weight and for safety.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum permissible weight is 728kg including the driver without fuel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes ballast was used to add weight and lower the center of gravity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prior to 2006, cars had V10 engines with 3 litre engines producing close to 1000 hp with top speeds reaching 375kph.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2006, FIA came up with a rule that stated all cars must have a naturally aspirated (no turbocharger or supercharger) 2.4 litre V8 engines. Turbochargers were banned in 1989.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since 2014, engines are 1.6l turbocharged for an improved fuel efficiency of 29%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2009 engines were limited to 18,000 rpm for engine reliability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engines consume close to 450lof air per second.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine is located between driver and the rear axle and forms a structural support of the car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2004, engines were required to last a race weekend and subsequently the number of engines that could be used for a season were reduced to 8 and now to 3. That means an engine has to last for more than one race which would reduce the cost and make the units more reliable.
-Fuel used is similar to normal petrol with a controlled mix and FIA requires fuel suppliers to submit samples for testing and can ask for a sample at any time during the course of a season.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transmission&quot;&gt;Transmission&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All cars have a semi-automatic gearbox with 8 forward and 1 backward gears.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carbon-titanium is used to make gearbox and is connected right behind the engine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paddles behind the steering wheels are used to upshift and downshift.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clutch is controlled by electro-hydraulics except when starting from a standstill when the driver operates a lever in the steering wheel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Limitations exist on the number of gearboxes over a season as well. Gearboxes must complete six consecutive races before being replaced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;steering-wheel&quot;&gt;Steering wheel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steering wheel houses many controls including gear shift, rev. limiter, fuel mix controller etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data related to various parameters are also displayed in LCD displays on the wheel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They weight around 1.3kg and can cost up to $50,000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tyres&quot;&gt;Tyres&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tyres used are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hypersoft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ultrasoft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supersoft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medium&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Superhard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intermediate(for partially wet conditions)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wet (rain tyres)
During rain, wet tyres can remove almost 250l of water a second from the track.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-systems&quot;&gt;Other systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aerodynamics are controlled by using spoilers in the front and rear.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the throttle is let go, the aerodynamic drag will slow down the car at the same rate at which a sports car decelerates under breaking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KERS (Kinetic Energy Recovery System) is used to give the car additional boost and stores the energy dissipated while braking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-facts&quot;&gt;Some facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Car costs anywhere between 6 to 8 millions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 800 parts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine normally lasts for few races. Earlier it was an engine per week. Revs up to 16,000 - 18,000 RPM.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tyres last for around 90-120 km.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can accelerate from 0 to 160 kph back to 0 in 4 sec.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drivers lose close to 3-4 kg every race.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At 130 kph, car has a downforce equal to its weight and can go upside down in a tunnel. Flight principles reversed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roughly 2600-3000 gear shifts, Monaco has the most number of shifts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1200 litres of fuel is used per race weekend. Efficiency of 70l/100km.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brake discs reach temperatures of 1000°C, exhaust pipe reaches 900°C and tyres reach 130°C during a race.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Champagne tradition started in 1950, locals fans presented a three litre bottle of champagne to the race winner Fangio.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1966, Jo Siffert in 24 hours of Le Mans opened a bottle of champagne which wasn’t sufficiently cooled. The cork flew up and resulted in the drink splashing on everyone. This tradition continues to this day with the exception of Bahrain Grand Prix where it champagne is replaced with sparkling fruit juice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2005, a BAR Honda car set an unofficial speed record of 413kph at Bonneville Speedway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/en/car-racing-barcelona-formula-1-1404063/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pixabay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 23:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/046-deconstructing-formula-one/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/046-deconstructing-formula-one/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
