<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writer &amp;amp; Geek Show</title>
    <description>We are Writer &amp; Geek, we make our listeners get excited about boring stuff one episode at a time. Writer and Geek Show is a science and tech podcast and we love geeking about tech, history, science, music and any other topic they can think of. In this show, we discuss a variety of topics and ramble on and on about them.
</description>
    <link>https://writerandgeek.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://writerandgeek.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 19:47:57 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 19:47:57 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why is a dog a dog and not wolf?</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;evo-what-evolution&quot;&gt;Evo… what? Evolution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theory of evolution states that chemicals randomly orgnaised themselves into a self replicating molecule. The simple self-replicating molecule then underwent mutation and formed the complex organisms that ever existed on the earth. The theory consists of basicaly three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is possible for the DNA of an organism to occasionally change, or mutate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The change brought about by a mutation is either beneficial, harmful or neutral.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As mutations occur and spread over long periods of time, they cause new species to form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mutations have seen to be affecting E-Coli bacteria which under right circumstances can replicate itself in every 20 minutes. By the process of mutation, certain bacteria can evolve which can be resistant to certain antibiotics. This is similar to certain insects becoming immune to DDT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;domestication&quot;&gt;Domestication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not all animals can be domesticated. Out of the 148 major terrestrial mammals, only 14 were domesticated and gthe theory is the for a species to be able to be domesticated, there are six charecterisitcs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficient diet&lt;/strong&gt;: Should be able to feed on cheap accessible food.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quick growth rate&lt;/strong&gt;: Should be able to mature and reproduce at a faster rate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ability to breed in captivity&lt;/strong&gt;: Should be able to breed under domestic conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pleasant disposition&lt;/strong&gt;: Should not be dangerous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tendency not to panic&lt;/strong&gt;: These animals should not have a tenency to panic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social structure&lt;/strong&gt;: Should follow a social structure like pack animals where a certain heirarchy is respected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the reason why animals like Zebra are difficult to be domesticated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dogs are amongst the oldest domesticated animals. Dogs were domesticated before cattle and even plants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;changes-in-animals-post-domestication&quot;&gt;Changes in animals post domestication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Animals become more tame, in some cases grow floppy ears, tail etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neural crest hypothesis suggests that deficits in the Neural Crest Cells which are the embryonic stem cells that produce various tissue types during embryogenesis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These changes do not usually get reversed if the animal is release back to the wild. &lt;strong&gt;Dingo&lt;/strong&gt; being an example.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reversion almost never happens. &lt;strong&gt;Dingos&lt;/strong&gt; are classic examples where in spite of staying apart from humans for thousands of years, thay haven’t shown any significant brain growth than normal dogs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paths-of-animals-into-domestication&quot;&gt;Paths of animals into domestication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commensal pathway&lt;/strong&gt;: Animals like dogs and cats who were attracted to human ways for resources available with human beings. Chickens too!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prey pathway&lt;/strong&gt;: Animals like the livestock belong to a category that were once hunted for food. They were domestiated mostly for food.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Directed pathway&lt;/strong&gt;: These include animals like horses,donkeys etc that could be used for purposes like transporation etc. and no necessarily for meat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pathways need not be exclusive. Animals may have followed multiple pathways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-russian-domesticated-fox&quot;&gt;The Russian Domesticated Fox&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dmitry Belyayev&lt;/strong&gt;: Belyayev conducted the &lt;em&gt;The Silver Fox Experiment&lt;/em&gt;. He believed that all the domesticated animals have been selected for tameness. He conducted an experiment which took up most the last 26 years of his life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He used a Siver fox, which is a variant of the &lt;em&gt;Red Fox&lt;/em&gt; because he felt that it is more social and related to dog.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1958, he directed his assistant Lyudmila Trut to visit various fur farm in Soviet Union and select the calmest foxes she could find.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiment began with 30 male foxes and 100 vixens, most of them from a commercial fur farm in Estonia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They were bred solely for tameness and weren’t trained to ensure that the resulting tameness was due to genetics and not due to training.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Darwin had stated that domesticated animals tend to have smaller heads, floppier ears, curlier tails and spotty coats to appear juvenile to humans. Belyayev wanted to test this theory as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Genetics had recieved some bad rap in post war Soviet, so Belyayev spoke about his research in terms of Phsycology rather than mention genes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Starting at month one throughout, the foxes were tested for their reactions to the experimenter. They would pet and handle the foxes and at when they reach sexual maturity at 7-8 months, they are assigned an overall tameness score.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During the end of 7-8 months they were categorised onto three classes based on their tameness index.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An &lt;em&gt;Elite&lt;/em&gt; class was later added that showed even more tameness and friendliness than class 1.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The experiment started showing rapid results and by the fourth generation, researchers were able to find results that was up to their expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An employee took a fox home and it responded to it’s name the same a way a dog does.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By tenth generation 18% of the population was elite group and by 20th generaion this number had risen to 35% and to around 80% in 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After around 40 generations, Belyayev’s foxes have floppy ears, transformation in skull size, curly tails, mating periods, changes in fur colour and even lost their fox odour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@berkaygumustekin?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Berkay Gumustekin&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Berkay Gumustekin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/055-domestication/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/055-domestication/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is smoking cool?</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The origin of tobacco can be traced back to 6000 BC, in the American continent. It was considered medicinal and used as a painkiller.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smoking cannabis can be traced back to 2000 BC, India. It is also mentioned in Atharvaveda.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cannabis smoking in the middle east was common, especially Hookah. Even women took part in it privately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christopher Columbus played a big part in getting it to the European continent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1531 - first tobacco cultivation in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 1600, tobacco became an integral part of the society as a good section started smoking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1560, Jean Nicot took tobacco with him to Spain from France&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1571, a Spanish doctor named Nicolas Monardes, apparently “found out” tobacco could cure 36 health problems (what a joke!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1588, Thomas Harriet, a Virginian, said that smoking gives the daily dose of tobacco. Not surprisingly, he died of nose cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;English King James I was one of the first to speak against smoking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tobacco used as an exchange during these time. The barter system did rely on tobacco.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Africa was introduced to tobacco by Arab traders in the 13th century, It was popularised by French merchants in 1600 by bringing tobacco to Senegal &amp;amp; Gambia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 17th century saw Japanese use a device called Kiseru. It was a long-stemmed device.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1760, Pierre Lorillard set up the Lorillard Tobacco Company in NYC. it is the oldest tobacco company in the US.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nicotine was discovered in 1826 and found to be harmful to humans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1836, Samuel Green mentioned that tobacco is an insecticide, a poison which can kill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chinese got into the habit of smoking opium due to colonialism. The British got them addicted to opium and it resulted in the Opium Wars.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chewing tobacco became popular amongst cowboys in the 19th century. It was more popular than smoking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 1901, smoking was catching up with 6 billion cigars and 3 billion cigarettes sold.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1902, Britisher, Philip Morris set up Marlboro brand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1913, R. J. Reynolds set up the Camel brand of cigarettes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;World Wars saw a tremendous increase in smoking. It was called soldier’s smoke and was included in the soldier’s ration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 1923, Camel took over 45% of the market in the US.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which led to Marlboro marketing it as women’s cigarette in 1924. They called it Mild as May. The number of women smokers tripled over the next few years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nazi Germany has one of the most powerful anti-smoking movement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During the 1950s evidence of smoking leading to lung cancer began popping up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1952, Kent Brand developed Micronite, a cigarette which contains asbestos. It was shelved shortly afterwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1953, Dr Ernst L. Wynders found that cigarette tar causes a tumour in mice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1956, first menthol cigarette was released by RJ Reynolds called Salem.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1964, regulations in cigarette advertisements were placed after the finding on Smoking and Health report made it clear that smoking causes lung cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1965, Britain takes cigarette commercials off television&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1966, health warnings started popping up on packets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1968, Bravo, a non-tobacco cigarette brand made of lettuce. Mega Failure!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US takes off cigarette advertisements in 1971&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the first national Great American Smokeout takes place in 1977. It is an annual event which takes place on the third Thursday of every November.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1982, it is found out that second-hand smoking also leads to lung cancer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1985, lung cancer overtakes breast cancer as the number one cause of women’s death.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;india-and-smoking&quot;&gt;India and Smoking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first act to add a statutory warning on packets came into existence in 1975&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public smoking banned in Kerala in 1999. The first state in India to do that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On September 8, 2000, the complete ban on tobacco and smoking advertisements came into effect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On Dec 1, 2004, prohibition of selling tobacco products within 100 yards of any educational institutions came into effect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2007, Chandigarh became first city smoke-free. Shimla followed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On Oct 2, 2008, public smoking was banned nationwide public&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In May 2009, mandatory pictorial warning covering at least 40% of the label came into effect. It also stated the use of only two languages on the packet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hookah ban carried out in many cities during 2011-12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On October 2, 2012, theatres implemented to play “Sponge” and “Mukesh” - two awareness advertisements before movies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On October 2, 2013, these were replaced by “Child” and “Dhuan”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use our Castbox Premium Coupon Code &lt;strong&gt;WRITER&lt;/strong&gt; to get six months premium menbership of castbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@rist_art?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Rist Art&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Rist Art&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/054-smoking/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/054-smoking/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Get yourself a Tattoo!</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-a-tattoo&quot;&gt;What is a tattoo?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Body modification where ink, dye or pigment is inserted into the dermis layer of the skin to change the colour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was considered uncivilised in the west until recently, tattoos carried symbolic meanings in many societies and culture since early ages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, tattooing became more popular art in the west.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The word tattoo, or tattow in the 18th century, from the Samoan word tatau, meaning “to strike”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In Europe, tattooing is speculated to have been practised during the upper palaeolithic period (Old stone age, between 50,000 and 10,000 years).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From evidence gained from the mummified skin, tattoos have been practised since the Neolithic times (new stone age. Approx 10,200 BC - 2000 BC).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direct evidence for the existence of tattoos exists only as far as 4000 years in history.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earliest tattoed human body is that of &lt;strong&gt;Ötzi the iceman&lt;/strong&gt; who lived between 3370 and 3100 BC and was found in the Ötztal Alps between Austria and Italy. Ötzi had a total of 61 tattoos in the form of groups of parallel lines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Several other mummified bodies have been recovered from various parts of the world including Egypt, South America, Siberia and Alaska.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chinese cemeteries in the Xinjiang region have been known to contain tattooed mummies dating back to 2100-550 BC.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was considered to be a barbaric practice and often prisoners were forcefully tattood on face&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greeks use tattoos for spy communications and used distinctive markings on their bodies to identify the ranks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tattooing was introduced to Japan by the Ainu people of East Asia. They had smiling tattoos on the faces of women.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In Europe, Britons, Danes and Norse used tattoos to identify the family.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emperor Constantine banned tattoo in AD 330&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pope Hadrian banned tattoo in the year 747 A.D. during the second council of Nicea and post Norman invasion in 1066, tattoos lost popularity from 12&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; to 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centuries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During this time tattoos were used to identify criminals in Japan. Lines were added during subsequent lines to eventually spell out the word &lt;em&gt;dog&lt;/em&gt;. Later tattoo became an art form and popular among the middle and lower class as ornate full body clothing was restricted to the royalty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;William Dampier&lt;/strong&gt;, a sailor and explorer was responsible for the revival of tattoos back in the west. He brought Polynesian Prince Giolo to London in 1691 who was completely tattooed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;James Cook&lt;/strong&gt; has been credited with bringing the word tattoo back to Europe after his travels to New Zealand and Tahiti.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nazis forcibly tattooed the prisoners for identification purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tattoo-ink&quot;&gt;Tattoo Ink&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Created from compounds of heavy metals like Cadmium, Chromium or Lead with Manganese or Aluminium salts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple needles penetrate into the dermis and deposit ink.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Immune systems (white blood cells) tries to engulf the pigment granule. Since the pigment granule is larger in size, the blood cells cannot easily remove the ink particles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Over times, tattoo fades as the pigments are carried to the liver through lymph nodes and removed from the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tattoo machine uses needles, circular formation for lines and brush like formation for shading.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Types of machines:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rotary: The rotary motion of a motor is converted into piston-like motion of the needle&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Coil type: An electromagnetic current is used to power the needle&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ink passes from the needles to the dermis layer of the skin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;removal&quot;&gt;Removal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lasers with frequencies in the range of picoseconds are used.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Laser shatters the pigments and reduces the size which makes it easier for the white blood cells to remove the particles from the body.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The shattering happens as the laser heats up one part of the ink particle resulting in a heat gradient and hence the particle rips apart.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frosting happens on the skin results from the shock wave that forms on the surface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@rominafa?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Romina Farias&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Romina Farias&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2018 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/053-tattoo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/053-tattoo/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A fireside chat on International Podcast Day ft. The Musafir Stories and The Passion People Podcast</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Wish you all a very happy International Podcast &amp;amp; Coffee Day. This is a special episode which will not feature our usual rambling. Saif and Naga from &lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/channel/the-musafir-stories-india-travel-podcast&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Musafir Stories&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/channel/the-passion-people-podcast&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Passion People Podcast&lt;/a&gt;, respectively, hijacked our show 😨 The interrogated us for more than 20 minutes to figure out the secret behind our mojo. So, sit back and listen ✌🏻&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hijacked their shows too. Links below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/posts/7027168-tms-specials-our-journey-so-far&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Our Journey So Far&lt;/a&gt; - The Musafir Stories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/posts/7027223-international-podcast-day-bonus&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Podcast Day - Bonus&lt;/a&gt; - The Passion People Podcast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 03:49:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/podcast-day/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/podcast-day/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The History of Vaccum Cleaner</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;vacuum-cleaner&quot;&gt;Vacuum Cleaner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vacuum cleaner, also known as a sweeper or hoover, is a device that uses an air pump to create a partial vacuum to suck up dust and dirt, usually from floors, and from other surfaces.
Basically, it is a device which sucks your home tidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2300 B.C. - First rudimentary forms of broom and cleaning tools came into existence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1797 - Levi Dickenson devised a broom with the use of sorghum bristles. The sorghum broom business exploded and by 1860 sorghum got the name broomcorn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1858 - Hiram Herrick patented a carpet sweeper which was the first American patent for a carpet sweeper. The device consisted of a rolling broom and dustpan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1860 - Daniel Hess produced a carpet sweeper which used suction through a rotating brush and bellows. It was completely manual and that is probably the reason why it was not successful. It was the first rudimentary design of a vacuum cleaner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1869 - Ives W. McCaffe came up with ‘Whirlwind’, the first manual vacuum cleaner which was upright. The belt driven, hand-powered device was sold for a retail price of $25 which would be around a whopping $450 in the present. This proved to be the reason for the unsuccessful run of the device.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1898 - A gasoline powered blower was developed by John S. Thurman, which had to be horse-drawn to locations due to its bulky nature. It was a moderately successful device which relied on blowing the dust into a receptacle instead of suction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1901 - Hubert Cecil Booth from England manufactured the ‘Puffing Billy’ which was also a bulky device but relied on suction. The gasoline-powered machine was later upgraded to electric power. It used a cloth filter to collect the dust. Puffing Billy was extremely successful and hotels started installing it in their compound. It was once also used to clean West Minister Abbey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During the same time, David T. Kenney came up with a vacuum cleaner which was powered by steam engine. But it did not succeed in getting much business due to its weight of 4000 pounds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1906 - Walter Griffiths came up with the first portable vacuum cleaner which used bellows and flexible pipe for suction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1906 -  Jame B. Kirby developed a vacuum cleaner that used water for dirt separation instead of a filter. It was called ‘Domestic Cyclone’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1907 - James Murray Spangler, a janitor from Ohio devised a vacuum cleaner with the use of a broom, electric rotating motor, and a pillowcase for dust collection. Because he did not get the funding, he sold the patent to William Henry Hoover in 1908.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1926 - Hoover redesigned the vacuum cleaner by adding a steel box for sturdiness and disposal filter bags to collect dust. It became a mainstay in the market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1997 - A Swedish company came up with ‘Electrolux Trilobite’, the first autonomous cordless robotic vacuum cleaner. This was made available to the consumers in 2001.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2004 - A British company came up with ‘Airider’, a vacuum cleaner which uses the technology of hovercrafts to float above the floor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Affiliate Links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the best vacuum cleaner available for you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2NKyLKW&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Micronic-AMI-VCD21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2NLPddF&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eureka Forbes Quick Clean DX (economic)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Car vacuum cleaner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2QxN6c5&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IGRID Car Vacuum Cleaner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to buy the vacuum cleaner we use, here is the link&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2xevYA8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Karcher WD 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@creativeexchange?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from The Creative Exchange&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;The Creative Exchange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 11:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/052-vaccum-cleaner/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/052-vaccum-cleaner/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ice-cream</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;ice-and-cream&quot;&gt;Ice and cream&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No introduction required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a colloidal emulsion which is made into a foam by incorporating air and then frozen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice cream is a mixture of water, ice, milk fat, milk protein, sugar and air.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The mixture is stirred well to incorporate air and is cooled below the freezing point and stored as semi-solid foam stored at low temperatures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accepted composition of ice-cream in the US according to Wikipedia (all percentages by weight):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater than 10% milkfat and usually between 10% and as high as 16% fat in some premium ice creams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9 to 12% milk solids-not-fat: this component, also known as the serum solids, contains the proteins (caseins and whey proteins) and carbohydrates (lactose) found in milk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 to 16% sweeteners: usually a combination of sucrose and glucose-based corn syrup sweeteners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2 to 0.5% stabilisers and emulsifiers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;55% to 64% water, which comes from the milk or other ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ice cream was consumed during the Achaemenid Empire in 500 BC. Ice was mixed with flavours and consumed during the summertime.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Persians also invented a dish with ice, rose water and vermicelli which was a primitive version of &lt;strong&gt;Falooda&lt;/strong&gt;. This was mostly reserved for the Royals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greeks weren’t behind, they also invented snow mixed with honey and fruits which was also sold in the markets of Athens.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hippocrates advocated eating ice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;China invented the real primitive form of ice-cream using milk and rice around 200 B.C. Snow and saltpetre was poured outside of containers filled with syrups to reduce the melting point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A few centuries later, during the time of Nero, ice was bought from the mountains to Rome and combines with fruits and served as delicacies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marco Polo bought the recipe back to Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In India, ice was shipped in from Hindukush mountains and used in sorbets and in making &lt;em&gt;Kulfi&lt;/em&gt; which came into existence around 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italian Dutchess Catherine de Medici married Henry II of France in 1533 and bought some Italian chef’s along with her who made flavoured ice. Flavoured ice became popular in France.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italian Francesco dei Coltelli opened an ice cream café in 1651 in Paris which became popular. During the next 50 years around 250 cafés opened in Paris.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charles I of England was fond of ice-cream and paid his chef to not to give away the recipe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the mid-eighteenth century, ice-cream became popular in the United States as well. George Washington was a big fan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the mid-nineteenth century, ice-cream became inexpensive and available to common people. This was mainly due to Carlo Gatti setting up a stand outside of Strand in 1851. He sold a scoop for one penny. He imported ice from Norway.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agnes Marshall popularised many ice-cream recipes in England.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice-cream appeared in Greece in 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;production&quot;&gt;Production&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Before refrigerators, ice-cream was meant only for the rich upper class. Ice was hard to come by.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice-cream was made in using the &lt;em&gt;pot freeze&lt;/em&gt; method where a large bowl was kept in a tub of ice and salt.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The mixture of salt and ice cooled the temperature of the ingredients within the bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salt partially melts the ice allowing it to absorb the latent heat and thus brings the temperature of the ingredients below the freezing point of water. This helps in freezing milk which has a lower freezing point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First, large-scale production in the US was by Jacob Fussell of Baltimore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;types&quot;&gt;Types&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sundae&lt;/strong&gt;: A type of ice-cream with one or more scoop of cream and syrup. It was a variation of ice-cream soda and due to restrictions on consuming soda on Sundays, soda was replaced with syrup. To avoid religious conflict changed the spelling to “ice-cream sundae”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice-cream cone&lt;/strong&gt;: Agnes Marshall’s cookery book had a recipe for serving ice cream in cones, but the practice is believed to be existing before that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Faludah or Faloodeh&lt;/strong&gt;: Popular Iranian ice-cream with vermicelli, rose water and sugar syrup.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gelato&lt;/strong&gt;: Italian frozen dessert with a lower milk fat content than ice cream.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice-cream sandwich&lt;/strong&gt;: A bar of ice-cream sandwiched between two cookies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frozen yoghurt&lt;/strong&gt;: Made with yoghurt instead of milk or cream.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;present-day&quot;&gt;Present day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US is the major consumer of ice-cream with about 23 litres per capita followed by Australia and New Zealand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;India is one of the largest producers of ice-cream and most of the production is consumed domestically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@harniche?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Harnish Ganatra&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Harnish Ganatra&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 11:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/051-ice-cream/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/051-ice-cream/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cryptography ft. Rupen Paul</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;thats-50&quot;&gt;That’s 50!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 50&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; episode, we sit down and talk with Rupen Paul, the star stand up comedian and upcoming podcaster about cryptography. This was a pleasant evening with rain, coffee and snacks. Occassional chewing noises are to be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sit back and enjoy our version of cryptography!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rupens-right-room&quot;&gt;Rupen’s Right Room&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rupen is also the host of an amazing podcast and we think that you should definitely check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/channel/the-right-room&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Right Room Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;books-mentioned&quot;&gt;Books mentioned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that these are affiliate links where we get paid a percentage for each purchase and this helps us in the production of the show. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2BQH6b4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Enigma: The Battle For The Code (Hugh Sebag-Montefiore)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Lxg7RC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Digital Fortress by Dan Brown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2PF4z1G&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sherlock Holmes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@mr_williams_photography?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Micah Williams&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Micah Williams&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/050-cryptography/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/050-cryptography/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An update on the flood situation</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;update&quot;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a quick update on the flood situation in Kerala and Karnataka:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Lrh4HlpQrI8?rel=0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the overwhelming support. Kerala and Karnataka need our support to get through the tough times due to heavy rains and floods. Let us continue our solidarity irrespective of religion, region, caste, language and other diversity. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@laicho?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Cherry Laithang&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Cherry Laithang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/flood-update/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/flood-update/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Serial Killer Files Part 5: Cyanide Mohan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mohan Kumar, infamously known as Cyanide Mohan is a serial killer who targeted women by offering them marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;details&quot;&gt;Details:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DOB: 1963&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place: Mangalore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marital status: Married thrice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Span of crime: 2005-2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of victims: 20&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Date of apprehension: October 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crime-history&quot;&gt;Crime history&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cyanide Mohan worked as a primary school teacher from 1980 to 2003.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He was fired from his job for allegedly pushing a woman off the Nethravathi when she refused his marriage proposal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The motive of the murders were to satisfy his sexual needs and to extort the valuables from his victims.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He used cyanide laced pills to kill his victims.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convicted for 5 murders of the 20 murders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He is his own attorney and successful appealed to convert one death penalty into a life sentence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He is also found to have committed bank frauds and forgeries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently serving two death penalties and two life sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@rawpixel?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from rawpixel&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;rawpixel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/049-serial-killer-cynide-mohan/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/049-serial-killer-cynide-mohan/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A request</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;kerala-needs-our-help&quot;&gt;Kerala needs our help&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kerala has been hit with torrential rains over past few weeks and things are getting really difficult down there. In this short conversation, we request you to be a part in helping to rebuild the God’s own country. Honourable Chief Minister of Kerala tweeted the details on how you can contribute to this cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://donation.cmdrf.kerala.gov.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chief Minister’s Distress Relief Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Here&amp;#39;s how you can help those affected by the unprecedented floods in Kerala. Now you can make donations online to Chief Minister&amp;#39;s Distress Relief Fund through the site,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/OFHTHlZ9by&quot;&gt;https://t.co/OFHTHlZ9by&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/KeralaFloods?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#KeralaFloods&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/StandWithKerala?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#StandWithKerala&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/XNlBKqdCUT&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/XNlBKqdCUT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; CMO Kerala (@CMOKerala) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CMOKerala/status/1029363568725110784?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 14, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@laicho?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Cherry Laithang&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Cherry Laithang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 05:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/a-request/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/a-request/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
