<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writer &amp;amp; Geek Show</title>
    <description>We are Writer &amp; Geek, we make our listeners get excited about boring stuff one episode at a time. Writer and Geek Show is a science and tech podcast and we love geeking about tech, history, science, music and any other topic they can think of. In this show, we discuss a variety of topics and ramble on and on about them.
</description>
    <link>https://writerandgeek.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://writerandgeek.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 16:35:07 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 16:35:07 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dyatlov Pass Incident</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;To the east of the Ural mountains, in Yekaterinburg city cemetery, there is a group grave of 9 members from a hiking group who died mysteriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arrived by train at Ivdel a town at the centre of the northern province of Sverdlovsk Oblast on 25&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; January 1959.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Took a truck ride to Vizhai (last settlement towards the north).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hikers purchased and had loaves of bread when they were in Vizhai to keep energy high.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started trek towards Otorten from Vizhai on 27&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; January.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yuri Yudin returned on 28&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; due to health issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, the hikers arrived at a highland area and started preparing for their climb. They saved surplus food in a wooded area for their return hike.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Snowstorms resulted in hikers being deviated from their intended path and ended up on the slopes of Kholat Syakhl (Dead Mountain).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Group decided to camp on the slopes of Kholat Syakhl instead of hiking all the way back into the wooded area about 1.5 km away. It is speculated that the group wanted to practice camping on a mountain slope.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dyatlov had told his sports club that he would send a telegram from Vizhai no later than 12&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; February and that it might take even longer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was not until 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; that the relatives of the hikers demanded a search be conducted for the missing hikers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The search party was mobilised and the military also took part in the search. On 26&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of February, the search party found the tent that was used by the hikers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tent was torn from inside and the hikers were missing. All the belongings including warm clothing and shoes were left behind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A set of footprints could be found heading away from the tent towards the woods, but after 500m, the tracks disappeared in the snow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the edge of the forest, under a Siberian Pine tree, there was a visible sign of a fire that was lit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first two bodies, Krivonischenko and Doroshenko were found shoeless near the fire site wearing only their underwears.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tree also had visible marks of someone having climbed it, with branches up to 5 metres broken. Someone seems to have climbed the tree to either escape from something or to look at something in distance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further search in the snow between the camp and the pine tree revealed the bodies of Dyatlov, Kolmogorova and Slobodin. Their poses suggested that they were trying to return to the campsite perhaps for food and warm clothing. They were found at a distance of 300, 480 and 630 metres from the tree respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The four remaining hikers were not found until 4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of May under 4 metres of snow around 75 metres away from the pine tree towards the woods. These four happened to be better dressed than others and the ones who died later were wearing the clothes of the ones who had died earlier. A hastily constructed den was found near the bodies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something happened on the night of 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; - 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; which lead to the death of all the hikers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;inquiry&quot;&gt;Inquiry&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An inquiry was started into the matter after the first five bodies were found. It was concluded that hypothermia was the reason for the deaths.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The finding of the four bodies later presented puzzling details which changed the course of the inquest.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Three of the four hikers had serious fatal injuries to the head and chest area.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doctors concluded that the force required to cause a similar injury would be something similar to that of a car hitting a person.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Except for Dubinina who was missing her tongue, eyes, parts of lips and a part of the skull, no major external wounds were found on the bodies. It was later claimed that these injuries were a result of her being face down on the water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;theories&quot;&gt;Theories&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The inquest concluded that all the hikers had died of a compelling natural force. The inquiry was stopped in May and all the files sent to secret archives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mansi&lt;/strong&gt;: Mansi do not frequently visit this area and the mountain and they were not territorial.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robbery&lt;/strong&gt;: No valuables were taken from the tent or the hikers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Animal attack&lt;/strong&gt;: No attack marks or animal footprints. This area wasn’t a hunting ground for animals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avalanche&lt;/strong&gt;: Most possible explaination but since the&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soviet Military Projects&lt;/strong&gt;: Bomb testing would’ve startled he hikers or caused avalanche. Radioactivity was detected in one of the hikers. Conspiracy theorists state that some of the hikers might have come across a secret military project and would’ve been killed by the military or died when they were pursuide. Interestingly, the bodies were searched for radioactivity which under normal circumstances is not a normal test. This raises further suspicions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Govt. Coverup&lt;/strong&gt;: Govt wanted the investigation to wrap up quickly. For three years after the incident, the area was closed for genral public.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrasound Theory&lt;/strong&gt;: Infrasound causing panic attack.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Katabatic Winds&lt;/strong&gt;: Strong winds blowing down the slope were also claimed to have taken the lives of the hikers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of control partying&lt;/strong&gt;: Excessive partying with alcohol or drugs, causing disorientation amongst the hikers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some hikers about 50km south of Dyatlov Pass who were hiking at the same time claim to have seen fireballs in the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://dyatlovpass.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dyatlovpass.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image:
&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@maiq?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Tom Morel&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Tom Morel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/066-dyatlov-pass/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/066-dyatlov-pass/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>More Horror feat. Indian Noir.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the second part of our conversation with Nikesh Murali, the producer of Indian Noir about horror and why humans are fascinated with the genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find Nikesh online:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/channel/indian-noir&quot;&gt;Indian Noir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nikeshmurali.net/&quot;&gt;Nikesh’s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@chillarea?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from sebastiaan stam&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sebastiaan stam&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 02:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/065-more-horror/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/065-more-horror/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why is horror so fascinating? Featuring Indian Noir.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode, we sit down and chat with Nikesh Murali, the producer of Indian Noir about horror and why humans are fascinated with the genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find Nikesh online:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/channel/indian-noir&quot;&gt;Indian Noir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nikeshmurali.net/&quot;&gt;Nikesh’s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@chillarea?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from sebastiaan stam&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sebastiaan stam&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 02:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/064-horror/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/064-horror/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is ejection seat a better alternative?.</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-ejection-seat&quot;&gt;What is ejection seat?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ejection seat is a safety mechanism primarily used in aircraft to save a pilot or a passenger by propelling the seat out of the disabled aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An explosive charge or rocket is used to propel the seat to a safe distance and a parachute takes care of the rest of the journey down to the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everald Calthorp&lt;/strong&gt; who earlier had invented parachutes devised an ejection seat that used compressed air.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Romanian inventor &lt;strong&gt;Ananstase Dragomir&lt;/strong&gt; proposed the modern layout for ejection seats in the late 1920s. The &lt;em&gt;parachuted cell&lt;/em&gt; design was tested on 25 August 1929 in Paris and got the design patented.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The technique used before ejection seat was to simply jump out of the aircraft which in most cases was difficult as it would cause injury and was dangerous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As with most of the things, World War II led to the development and perfection of parachutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heinkel&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;SAAB&lt;/strong&gt; developed the ejection seat independently. These early models were compressed air powered seats. &lt;strong&gt;Heinkel HE 280&lt;/strong&gt;, the prototype jet fighter, had an ejection system built into it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-process&quot;&gt;The Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there arises a scenario where ejection is imminent, the command “eject” is used as an early warning that a possible ejection is coming up in next 30 or so seconds. At the critical moment, the command “bailout” is used and the crew ejects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sequence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the pilot activates the ejection system, first the canopy is blown off or opened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pilot and the seat are launched through the opening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During ejection, a catapult propels the seat up the rails and then the rocket engine takes over.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The canopy forms another part of the ejection system. Most of the aircraft are designed in a way where the canopy is blown off the aircraft. In some cases to avoid delay or seat hitting the canopy, a specially designed canopy filled with explosive charges embedded within the acrylic canopy which when initiated, shatters the canopy above and the seat is ejected a few seconds later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In some other aircraft without canopy, the seats are ejected through hatches. B-52 bombers had ejection seats that were ejected through the hatches, four in the roof and two on the floor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@vishu_gowda?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Vishu Gowda&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Vishu Gowda&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 02:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/063-ejection-seat/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/063-ejection-seat/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beer Talk: Life 'n' stuff</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode, the boys sit down to discuss life ‘n’ stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/062-life-n-stuff/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/062-life-n-stuff/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Personal Finance ft. Naga from Passion People Podcast</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode, Vishnu is joined by friend and fellow podcast producer Naga Subramanya from The Passion Poeple Podcast to discuss personal finance. Vishnu is a noob and Naga is an expert when it comes to personal finance. Enjoy their conversation, there are many gems of knowledge in this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the stuff we discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Power of compounding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mutual funds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saving then spending&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Credit Cards and Debt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Insurance and why term insurance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can reach out to Naga here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://audioboom.com/channel/the-passion-people-podcast&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Passion People Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thepassionpeop1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Passion Poeple Podcast on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Naga’s email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:naagasubramanya@gmail.com&quot;&gt;naagasubramanya@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@sharonmccutcheon?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Sharon McCutcheon&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Sharon McCutcheon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/061-personal-finance/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/061-personal-finance/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cholanaikkans: The Lost Tribe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Cholanaikkans are an ethnic group of India, primarily inhabiting the southern Kerala State, especially Silent Valley National Park. They are one of the last remaining hunter-gatherer tribes of the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Population: 190-200 (2001 census: 360~)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Found in the late 1970s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Live in caves and rely on hunting and gathering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not cultivate due to the destruction of produce by animals such as elephants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Said to have moved to South due to natural disasters such as floods or fleeing due to their defeat under the dynasties from the North&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worships trees and follow animism which is the belief that everything (living or non-living) is bound by some spiritual connection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are short in stature, wheatish to dark complexion, and well-built&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have their own distinctive language&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow a patriarchal family structure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The literacy rate is around 16% with one graduate among them. Most drop out after one semester in school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We also talk about the Sentinelese from the Sentinel Islands. Enjoy!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/people/23619903@N00&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dhruvaraj S&lt;/a&gt; from India - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/dhruvaraj/251931897/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A Cholanaikkan Nilambur&lt;/a&gt;. Cropped 1:1 ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/060-cholanaikkans/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/060-cholanaikkans/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The humble toilet.</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;history-of-toilets&quot;&gt;History of toilets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toilets and sewers came into being as early as 3000 B.C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mohenjodaro had earliest forms of toilet which resembled western toilets. Waste was deposited into pits or drains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In Harappa, a primitive form of water cleaning toilet was used which utilised flowing water to remove waste.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Indus valley civilisation is well known for its network of sewers built under the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the west, toilets that used water were built in the Orkney Islands on the northern tip of Scotland dating back to 3100 B.C - 2500 B.C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 18th century B.C, toilets made appearances in Egypt, parts of Greece and Persia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remains of toilets have been found from a Neolithic village in Vietnam dating back to 1500 B.C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Romans used public toilets along with public baths. These toilets were elevated platforms over sewers that were periodically flushed with water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greeks and Romans also used &lt;strong&gt;Chamber Pots&lt;/strong&gt; that were brought to public meal and drinking parties! Yeah, let them sink in for a moment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Han dynasty in China used &lt;strong&gt;Pig toilets&lt;/strong&gt;. An outhouse was connected to a pigsty and the waste was consumed by the pigs. Hence the reputation Pork!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During medieval times &lt;strong&gt;Garderobes&lt;/strong&gt; were used as toilets, especially in Castles. Basically, a flat piece of wood or stone spanning from wall to wall with a hole in the middle. The holes were placed above pipes that dropped the waste outside the wall of the room. Usually these rooms were placed away from bedrooms to prevent smell and sometimes near kitchen or fireplace for warmth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chamber pots were also extensively used in medieval times. The waste was excreted into pots made of metal or ceramic and they were emptied into street gutters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rural Denmark, until 18&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, had no toilets. Instead, people defecated in farmlands so that the waste could be used as manure for the crop. Cycle of life!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, to avoid the clogging on gutters around the streets, cesspools and cesspits were dug near houses to collect waste. The toilet was connected to the cesspools by a pipe with sometimes water to clean the waste. &lt;strong&gt;Gong farmers&lt;/strong&gt; cleaned out these pits by pumping out the liquid waste and removing the solid waste. This was done mostly during the night and the solid waste came to be known as the &lt;strong&gt;night soil&lt;/strong&gt; and was used as manure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While water closets were something that wealthy could afford, the working class and in towns and cities, &lt;strong&gt;Privy Midden&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Pail closets&lt;/strong&gt; were used. Privy midden was an outhouse with a waste dump and had a bad reputation for being difficult to clean. Pail closet was a toilet with a bucket into which people defecated and local authorities cleaned out the buckets on regular basis and either got rid of the waste or used it as manure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was not until early 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century that public sanitation was considered a necessity and mid 19&lt;sup&gt;the&lt;/sup&gt; century is when underground sewer networks were constructed to carry away waste.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The building codes in London did not require an indoor toilet until after the First World War.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water closet, although invented during the Tudor era in 1596 by Sir John Harington, Queen Elizabeth’s godson, it wasn’t perfected until 1770 by &lt;strong&gt;Alexander Cumming&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Joseph Bramah&lt;/strong&gt;. Around 1850s, water cosets started moving inside the houses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-india&quot;&gt;In India&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manusmriti: At least 40 hands distance is to be observed while urinating near a river or temple and defecation should be at least at a distance of 400 hands.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toilets were constructed only after Mughals came to India.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/2365725066780452/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;O2Pod Meetup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://podhead.co/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Podhead&lt;/a&gt;: Check out the newsletter and amazing podcast recommendations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@gabor?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Gabor Monori&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Gabor Monori&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/059-toilet/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/059-toilet/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Serial Killer Files Part 6: The gangster from Madras</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Auto Shankar is the nickname of an Indian serial killer Gowri Shankar. Shankar and his gang were found guilty of six murders, committed over a period of two years in 1988–1989.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name: Gowri Shankar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Known as: Auto Shankar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DOB: January 21, 1954,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place: Kangeyanallur village, Vellore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of victims: 6&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cause of death: Hanging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death: April 27, 1995&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crime Spree: 1988-1989&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@fancycrave?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Fancycrave&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Fancycrave&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/058-serial-killer-auto-shankar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/058-serial-killer-auto-shankar/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The wonderful chocolate</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;chocolate&quot;&gt;Chocolate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chocolate is a magic stuff made of roasted ground cocoa seeds. One of the most popular dessert ingredients. Needs no introduction, of course, chocolate can be used in a solid, liquid (choco syrup) and in many other forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The word &lt;strong&gt;chocolate&lt;/strong&gt; comes from the &lt;strong&gt;Nahuatl&lt;/strong&gt; word &lt;em&gt;chocolātl&lt;/em&gt;. Nahuatl was spoken in the valley of Mexico during the Spanish conquest of Aztec in the 16th century.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chocolate has been very popular in desserts and other forms of food and African countries are leading producers of cocoa even though it originated in the Americas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Western Africa produces about two-thirds of the world’s cocoa and Ivory coast produces about half of it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Types of chocolate:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dark chocolate&lt;/strong&gt;: Dark chocolate is a mixture of cocoa, fat and sugar. More the amount of cocoa, more bitter the chocolate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unsweetened chocolate&lt;/strong&gt;: This is unsweetened chocolate liquor called bitter or baking chocolate. It’s pure ground cocoa.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Milk chocolate&lt;/strong&gt;: Milk chocolate either contains milk powder of condensed milk with a minimum of 20-25% of cocoa depending on the country.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;White chocolate&lt;/strong&gt;: White chocolate contains cocoa butter, milk and sugar and no cocoa solids, that differentiates it from milk chocolates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the early history of chocolate (around 4000 years), chocolate was mostly used as a bitter beverage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence has been found that chocolate was cultivated in present-day Mexico around 1900 B.C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also believed to be fermented and consumed an alcoholic beverage around 1400 B.C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christopher Columbus came across cocoa beans during his fourth mission to Americas when his crew seized a native canoe filled with cocoa.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spanish explorer &lt;strong&gt;Hernán Cortés&lt;/strong&gt; came across chocolate in its true form in the court of Montezuma, who was the ruler of Tenochtitlan, capital of Aztec. The cocoa beverage was served in the gold cups and supposedly gave them power over women. The drink was said to be frothy with a very unpleasant taste but was highly esteemed by the natives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chocolate made its way into Europe following the Spanish conquest of Aztec. It was used initially as medicine to treat abdominal pain and later sugar or honey was added to make it into a sweetened beverage and was served in the court. In the next century, chocolate became a favourite in Europe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chocolate cultivation saw a rise and resulted in an increase in the slave trade. The &lt;strong&gt;Chocolaterie Lombart&lt;/strong&gt;, was the first chocolate company established in 1760 in France.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Industrial revolution accelerated the production of Cocoa.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coenraad van Houten&lt;/strong&gt;, a Dutch chemist, added alkaline salts to chocolate which helped in reducing its bitterness. In 1828, he devieda method to remove much of the cacao butter from chocolate liquor which made production cheaper and gave more consistency to chocolate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This cocoa called &lt;strong&gt;Dutch cocoa&lt;/strong&gt; also helped in creating chocolate in solid form in 1847 when &lt;strong&gt;Joseph Fry&lt;/strong&gt; added melted cacao butter back to chocolate to make it mouldable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In mid 1875, &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Peter&lt;/strong&gt;, a Swiss chocolatier, invented milk chocolate by adding powdered chocolate back to the liquor. Powdered milk used in this process was invented by &lt;strong&gt;Henri Nestlé&lt;/strong&gt;, founder of Nestlé. They later created the Nestlé company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The conching machine, a surface scraping mixer and agitator was invented in the year 1879 by &lt;strong&gt;Rudolf Lindt&lt;/strong&gt;, a Swiss chocolate manufacturer, which further improved the quality of the chocolate by giving is a smooth &lt;em&gt;melt-in-mouth&lt;/em&gt; consistency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In England, &lt;strong&gt;Cadbury&lt;/strong&gt; had started manufacturing boxed chocolates in 1868.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During the &lt;em&gt;World Columbian Exposition&lt;/em&gt; at Chicago held in 1893, &lt;strong&gt;Milton S. Hershey&lt;/strong&gt;, American chocolatier and philanthropist purchased the chocolate processing equipment and started Hershey’s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chocolate is made from cocoa beans. There are about 40 cocoa beans in a cocoa fruit. These beans are dried and fermented. The tree is called &lt;strong&gt;Cacao&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Three main varieties are &lt;strong&gt;Criollo&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Forastero&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Trinitario&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Criollo is the rarest of the three and is native to Central America, Carribean and Northern part of South America. They are difficult to grow and provide very low yield.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forastero is the most commonly grown version and commonly found in Amazon basin and Africa. They have a more chocolaty flavour which lasts for a shorter amount of time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trinitario is a hybrid of Criollo and Forastero which originated in Trinidad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process&lt;/strong&gt;: Cacao pods are removed from the tree and the beans with pulp are removed and placed in bins to enable fermentation. The fermentation takes up to a week and results in the chocolate flavour. Pods are harvested when they are ripe or the cocoa content would be less. Dried beans are transferred to a facility where the shell is removed to extract the nib. The nib is then ground and liquefied to chocolate in purest form as chocolate liquor. Cocoa solids and cocoa butter can be extracted from this liquor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conching&lt;/strong&gt;: Conching is processed by which the texture of the chocolate is smoothened. Chonche is a container which contains metal beads that act as grinders. The frictional heat keeps the chocolate in liquid form. High quality chocolate is conched for 72 hours and lesser grade chocolates are conched for 5-6 hours. The conched chocolate is then stored in containers at 40-50 degree Celsius.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tempering&lt;/strong&gt;: Tempering is a process to prevent uncontrolled crystallisation of cocoa butter in chocolate which results in crystals of varying sizes. Cocoa butter gave the chocolate its rigidity when solid at room temperature and when heated, the crystalline structure of cocoa butter breaks down and chocolate becomes liquid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Storage&lt;/strong&gt;: Chocolate is very susceptible to temperature and humidity changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@simonevdk?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Simone van der Koelen&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;Simone van der Koelen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 06:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://writerandgeek.com/057-chocolate/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://writerandgeek.com/057-chocolate/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Regular</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
